Good morning today is May 8th it is the 12th of אייר
Iyar the 27th day of the עומר Omer and today's דף Daf
is ק"ז Kuf Zayin in בבא בתרא Bava Batra we're in the
seventh פרק Perek פרק בית כור Perek Beit Kor and we are
halfway through a סוגיא Sugya actually about inheritance. Now the real inheritance
סוגיות Sugyot are going to come up at the end in the
ninth and tenth פרקים Perakim but we have a little taste of
it now and get to see one of the core מחלוקות Machlokot
related to inheritance questions. כור Kor בית כור Beit Kor core מחלוקות
Machlokot
have to get some puns in early because the rest of it's
not going to be very funny. All
right. So we're on the second line the second line of ק"ז
Kuf Zayin עמוד א' Amud Aleph איתמר. Itmar. So this is the
second half of the סוגיא Sugya that we saw yesterday. Yesterday's סוגיא
Sugya talked about if there were two brothers who divided the inheritance
and then a third brother shows up to try to join in
in their inheritance and how do they re-divide it or how do
they deal with that. So we have a similar kind of problem.
איתמר אחים שחלקו Itmar achim she-chalku there were two or perhaps more
brothers who had divided an inheritance ובא בעל חוב ונטל חלקו של
אחד מהם u-va ba'al chov ve-natal chelko shel echad me-hem and then
a creditor comes who has a lien on the father's property. It's
important that the debt is owed already from the estate that's what
the problem is is that the creditor
seized
property that was only inherited by one of the brothers. So that
is let's make it simple we had one father with two sons
and the two sons split the property and now that the creditor
has seized one of them so this brother has no inheritance and
the other brother has a full inheritance. So how do we deal
with that? רב אמר בטלה מחלוקת Rav amar batla machloket so רב
Rav says that the original division gets canceled and they go and
re-divide the remaining property.
Does he make an adjustment if I build a skyscraper on there?
Do you have to reimburse me for half the cost of my
skyscraper?
There would have to be well presumably what they mean is they
re-assess based on the value at the time of the inheritance.
Right so the expenses.
Right so the expenses are your expenses and you get the benefit
from that.
Like half of that? Meaning if it was.
No meaning if you took your inherited land and built a subdivision
or whatever then that's all your investment and you get the benefits
from that. So the question so I see what you're saying is
you've set up a situation where the property I feel like the
compensation would have to go to the other brother based on the
value of the land. But again it has to be assessed. You
know part of this challenge is going to come up in the
second סוגיא Sugya is a question of assessment and how to break
down those things. So often it gets to be a bit discretionary
in terms of the dayanic splitting it up. Yeah.
Also we assume that the חוב Chov is not like a personal
thing between the brother and the בעל חוב? Ba'al Chov?
Right exactly it's the father's debt. It's the father's debt. Otherwise it
doesn't make sense this case. It has to be that the father
had a debt with this בעל חוב. Ba'al Chov. The sons maybe
didn't know about it or they were hoping he wasn't going to
come to collect. They divided the property and then the בעל חוב
Ba'al Chov came and rather than trying to deal with them as
a corporate group to deal with the estate collectively he goes just
to one brother and seizes the property. So רב אמר בטלה מחלוקת
Rav amar batla machloket רב Rav says that because of this change
of circumstance the original division of property is canceled out and they
have to re-divide. שמואל אמר ויתר Shmuel amar vitar he basically loses
out. That is this brother who got his property
seized tough luck that's the reality. Why? We're going to see. They're
going to give some explanations for this. In the end the רשב"ם
Rashbam has an extended discussion. I'm going to just read רב אסי
Rav Assi next and then I'll try to go back a little
bit and explain. רב אסי אמר נוטל רביע בקרקע ורביע במעות Rav
Assi amar notel revi'a be-karka u-revi'a be-ma'ot רב אסי Rav Assi says
you take one quarter of the land and one quarter of the
cash.
Who's the who's the בעל חוב? Ba'al Chov?
The brother. The brother who just who lost out
gets a quarter from his brother
and
cash from his brother.
No. So רשב"ם Rashbam says it doesn't make any sense that it
would be and it must be ו' Vav serving as an or.
Either
he takes one quarter of the remaining field or one quarter of
its value in cash.
So that would be more or less the same as what רב
Rav said. בטלה מחלוקת.
Batla machloket. Right. So it seems like רב אסי's Rav Assi position
is that we רב אסי Rav Assi himself a later אמורא Amora
is unsure whether the הלכה Halakha should follow רב Rav or שמואל
Shmuel so רב אסי Rav Assi says it's a מחלוקת Machloket I'll
split some kind of a פשרה. Peshara. Very often in the ש"ס
Shas we see a three-way מחלוקת Machloket where there are two extreme
positions and the third position often a later position. try to reconcile
them halfway in between.
Is רב אסי Rav Assi much later?
He's not much later, he's one generation later. Okay, so what's the
rationale for רב's Rav position? Why does רב Rav say בטלה מחלוקת?
batla machloket? Because רב's Rav position, the גמרא Gemara says, רב אמר
בטלה מחלוקת קסבר האחין שחלקו יורשין הן. Rav amar batla machloket kasavar
ha'achin she'chalku yorshin hein. רב Rav says that when brothers take an
inherited property and subdivide it, they are like יורשין, yorshin, they are
like inheritors. ושמואל אמר ויתר קסבר האחין שחלקו לקוחות הוו. u'Shmuel amar
viter kasavar ha'achin she'chalku lakochot havu. And שמואל Shmuel thinks that when
brothers subdivide the property they are like purchasers. That is what, that
is when, one second
Michael, please don't interrupt, I'm sorry, I'm in the middle of a
sentence.
That is רב's Rav understanding of how this division of the inherited
property works is that the entire field is inherited by the heirs
as a corporate ownership. And when they go to subdivide it, that
means each of them gets their share. So they, oh there's a
nice picture here, that's not a useful picture for this. Okay.
So the entire field is in front of them, they go to
claim their portion of the field and רב Rav says יש ברירה.
yesh brera. The principle of ברירה brera comes to say that once
they've chosen the land that they're going to inherit, it becomes clarified
retroactively that that is what they were meant to inherit, quote unquote,
originally. So therefore they are like יורשין, yorshin, that is they've inherited
this field exactly. שמואל Shmuel says אין ברירה. ein brera. שמואל Shmuel
says there's no such principle of ברירה brera or ברירה brera doesn't
apply to this case and therefore they are לקוחות הוו. lakochot havu.
That is each brother is as if buying half of the corporately
owned or jointly owned inherited land for himself, but it's a two-stage
process according to שמואל. Shmuel. Michael, you had a question.
No, I was just going to say, like, you know, like the
aspect of you get to the whole thing about מחזירין ביובל machzirin
b'yovel or not.
Right. So that's going to come up later as well and this
becomes the core, perhaps the core מחלוקת machloket about how inheritance works,
ירושה, yerusha, when we say האחין שחלקו, ha'achin she'chalku, are they when
brothers divide, when the heirs, not only brothers, when the heirs divide
their inheritance are they dividing it as their inheritance or is it
considered a second stage and they're like purchasers? If they're buying it,
then it's purchasing without אחריות, achrayut, they're purchasing it without any kind
of guarantee, very high liability, and therefore if according to שמואל Shmuel
if this בעל חוב ba'al hov comes and claims his debt, then
the one who loses out loses out because he's like a לקוח,
lokeach, he's like someone who bought the field from the estate.
So I think you've just answered my question, these brothers have inherited
this one large plot of land, correct?
And they split it in half.
Wait, right, so is the מחלוקת machloket that שמואל Shmuel says once
they split it that's no longer the act of an heir, that's
an act of an owner of a piece of property. Right.
Ah, so then everyone would agree that before they split they're heirs,
right? It's a נחלה. nachala. Right.
So this is the inheritance. Okay. According to this שמואל Shmuel thinks
it's a two-stage process, this entire piece of land is jointly owned,
when they come to divide it that's a process of being a
לקוח, lokeach, that's purchasing it from the estate, corporate estate.
And רב Rav would say that both of those moments, the getting
possess-
possessing the whole plot and then figuring out who owns what part
of it is all part of the inheritance process.
For one of two reasons, either because רב Rav thinks it counts
as only one stage process, that is each of them getting half
is just what is the inheritance, or it's ברירה, brera, that is
once they've divided it we say ברירה, brera, we say that retroactively
this counts as if it was the original process.
It's essentially the same thing, it's just a matter of the cognitive
mechanism.
Maybe. But also this of course is going to touch into all
of the, I think, 12 other סוגיות sugyot in ש"ס Shas that
talk about ברירה, brera,
so ברירה brera is one of the most far-reaching principles, just to
have a handle on it. Many of the סוגיות sugyot contradict and
I think the הלכה halakha conclusion more or less is in דאורייתא
de'oraita fields, arenas of הלכה halakha we usually say אין ברירה ein
brera and in דרבנן de'rabbanan areas of הלכה halakha we usually say
יש ברירה. yesh brera. But that's just sort of a compromise to
try to sort out the details between the different סוגיות. sugyot. Yeah
Michael.
Just looking at this, I mean I'm just looking at the little
letters in the margin, the רמב"ם Rambam has בטלה מחלוקת batla machloket
but also says כשמואל.
k'Shmuel. Well, we'll have to look inside, I don't remember now exactly,
but we have a הלכתא hilcheta at the end of the סוגיא
sugya so we're not done yet.
Does it tell us the הלכה halakha over here? What?
Does it tell us the הלכה? halakha? Well, we're going to get
to that. So so the point is רב אסי, Rav Assi, רב
אסי Rav Assi is the third position. So we had רב Rav
thinks that רב Rav says יש ברירה, yesh brera, רב Rav says
that it's like ירושה, yerusha, שמואל Shmuel says אין ברירה, ein brera,
שמואל Shmuel says they're like לקוחות. lakochot. And רב אסי Rav Assi
says there's one quarter position. That is, this half is taken away
by the בעל חוב. ba'al chov. This brother goes over here and
he gets not a half because that would be what רב Rav
says, he gets one quarter. He gets only half of the half.
Okay, that's רב אסי's Rav Assi position because he says this half
is debated, so they split it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara explains,
yeah?
Can you just go simplify one more level? Sure.
Is שמואל Shmuel saying, is רב Rav saying
that
they each got the land that was meant for them to get,
right?
Halachically we see it when they subdivide it as if each was
somehow destined to get that portion. Right. But that's only a retroactive
process. What that means is then if something happened to half of
it, we can go back and reassess because it's always, it was
not like he bought this land, it was like when he got
this he inherited it. But if the creditor comes and seizes this,
then it's like the entire inheritance was only this half, again retroactively.
So then he can go back and claim half of this.
So how do you, what's the time sequence in terms of the
word retroactive?
In other words, that's a big debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. How
retroactive is retroactive and how do these mechanisms work is a huge
topic as to when this
creditor
came.
Right. So our point, time point number one is they inherited their
property from their father. Time point number two is the creditor comes.
Time point number three is this brother, we'll call him שמעון, Shimon,
goes to his brother ראובן Reuven and says I don't know what
to do, I want my inheritance.
So what do you mean by half the cash, רב אסי? Rav
Assi?
So רב אסי Rav Assi says either he gets one quarter of
the remaining field or he gets its value in cash from his
brother. Value now? Now. Presumably now. Perhaps it doesn't fluctuate so much
because let's
say, you know, you can question either way. If it went up,
if it appreciated, you know? Yeah, no, for sure.
It seems to be one quarter based on the value based on
how much this debt was because the רשב״ם Rashbam explains the reason
he can claim cash is because he can say if he had
had cash he would have paid off the creditor by cash and
he seized the land. So you know all of these kind of
questions and we know throughout ש״ס Shas actually sometime during the Amoraic
period there was a switch from seeing real estate as a more
reliable asset to seeing cash as more reliable. So it sort of
depends on the economy which would be preferred. If he's given an
option, either real estate or cash, is also interesting because it doesn't
mean one is preferred over the other. Yeah, Charlie?
These are, I point out these are Babylonian אמוראים. Amoraim.
Well רב אסי, Rav Assi, yeah, all three are Babylonian.
In the land of Israel you would never prefer cash in this,
of course, right.
In this era, that's exactly the point, is that the shift, as
we go from especially from the משנה Mishnah to the תלמוד בבלי,
Talmud Bavli, there's a shift from a real estate economy to a
cash economy.
Alright, so I'm sorry, when you say half the cash, whose option
is that to choose whether
he gets, presumably it's ראובן's Reuven choice, meaning if he wants to
retain this entire field then he can pay off cash instead. But
the claim, the claim that שמעון Shimon can make on his brother
is give me a quarter of the field or give me its
value in cash. Again, it's kind of strange the way רב אסי
Rav Assi says it. The רשב״ם Rashbam has to kind of do
the footwork to say that the ו׳ vav means or, one or
the other, because otherwise he's just agreeing with רב. Rav.
Yes.
I'm missing the connection between the concept of יש ברירה, yesh breira,
meaning this is what you were destined to get, and how that
means re-divide as opposed to tough luck.
Right. It means that predicated on the assumption that this entire field
was being inherited, each brother got half. But when the situation changes,
there's room to reassess because it's all part of a retroactive process.
Like once they get their fair share, it means it was part
of the original whole. But what this means is then if this
gets taken away and the fact is the debt predates the inheritance,
so that's the whole point, is there were liens on the property
against both of them. So רב Rav is saying because this debt
applied to the entire property, the fact that the creditor seized only
this field rather than seizing this half this way means that he
can come back and claim on the other half because it was
all part of the original inheritance. It's sort of one process. Okay.
Okay.
רב אסי, Rav Assi, so what does רב אסי Rav Assi say?
רב אסי מיסתפקא ליה אי יורשין הוו אי לקוחות הוו. Rav Assi
mistaklei i yorshin havu i lakochot havu. So רב אסי Rav Assi
disagrees, is unsure whether to hold like רב Rav or like שמואל.
Shmuel. הלכך נוטל רביע בקרקע ורביע במעות. Hilkach notel revi'a bekarka verevi'a
bemose. So he says you take one quarter either in the real
estate or in the cash. אמר רב פפא הלכתא בכל הני שמעתתא
כרב. Amar Rav Papa hilcheta bekhol hani shema'ata k'Rav. So, right, so
that's from yesterday. So רב פפא Rav Papa says the הלכה halacha
is like
רב. Rav. אמימר אמר בטלה מחלוקת. Amemar amar batla machloket. והלכתא בטלה
מחלוקת. Vehilcheta batla machloket. And the הלכה halacha follows רב. Rav. It
just It's interesting because here it seems like we're talking about a
case of דיני dinei and usually we follow שמואל Shmuel in cases
of דיני. dinei. It may be that because רב אסי Rav Assi
is at least somewhat in agreeance with רב Rav that we end
up deciding like רב Rav or it may be just that this
is a sort of an exceptional case. To point out part of
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, I think it's this long רשב"ם Rashbam towards the
bottom. Now I can't see which דיבור המתחיל dibbur hamat'chil it is,
sorry. But רשב"ם Rashbam here points out that רש"י Rashi in בבא
קמא Bava Kama
understood this סוגיא sugya differently because it comes up there in the
first פרק perek in בבא קמא. Bava Kama. And רשב"ם Rashbam explicitly
disagrees with his grandfather. He says זקני פירש הכא zekeni peresh hacha
and I explain differently. So just to tell you, I've been explaining
it to you like רשב"ם Rashbam says. רש"י Rashi sees it a
little bit different. And רש"י Rashi thinks that רב אסי's Rav Assi
position is the one-quarter plus one-quarter is what רש"י Rashi thinks. And
it seems like that's because רש"י Rashi thinks רב אסי's Rav Assi
position is not half רב Rav and half שמואל. Shmuel. It's actually
half רב Rav and half another possibility which is half יורש yoresh
and half לוקח lokeach with אחריות, achrayus, with liability. So according to
רש"י Rashi you would get half of the remaining field but half
of it in real estate and half cash equivalent because he has
an insurance on this half of the field that he had inherited.
But רשב"ם's Rashbam critique of רש"י's Rashi position is that it doesn't
make sense that רב אסי Rav Assi just sort of literary, the
way the structure of the סוגיא sugya goes, should be that רב
אסי Rav Assi should be 50-50 between רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
It is uncommon to find a third position in this kind of
debate where the third position is not related to both of the
previous positions, like I mentioned before. Like for example, the debate we
have different סוגיות, sugyot, I'm trying to remember, there's one in מגילה
Megilla where there's a debate about the ברכות brachot after the מגילה.
Megilla. And there's one אמורא amora says like this and one אמורא
amora says like this, and רב פפא Rav Papa says okay, say
both. That is, he takes the two previous positions and kind of
combines them. So here too, רשב"ם's Rashbam argument is that רב אסי's
Rav Assi position should be a combination or a ספק safek between
רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, not between רב Rav and an unstated
third opinion. Okay, so that's just the debate there between רשב"ם Rashbam
and רש"י Rashi how to understand this סוגיא. sugya. So even though
we don't have רש"י Rashi on the page, we have his שיטות
shitot sneaking back in a little bit as well. Excuse me.
Yeah. Does this conclusion say anything about whether we hold יש ברירה?
yesh brera?
So it sounds like in this case if we פוסקין pasken like
רב, Rav, then we are saying יש ברירה yesh brera in this
case, which like I said before is because this is a ירושה
yerusha case. It sounds like it's a דאורייתא d'oraitta סברא svara of
הלכה, halacha, which is not something we usually... right. It sounds like
a little bit of an exception and that's part of the challenge
with dealing with all of those ברירה brera סוגיות. sugyot. You have
to see it in the larger context and compare them and already
for the ראשונים Rishonim it was a lot of work to sort
out those details. Okay, the next סוגיא. sugya. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Now we're switching a little bit. Yes.
Did you say in דאורייתא d'oraitta we usually don't say יש ברירה?
yesh brera?
Usually in דאורייתא d'oraitta we say אין ברירה ein brera and in
דרבנן d'rabanan we say יש ברירה. yesh brera. That's sort of the
conclusion as it comes across
הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh nowadays. Most kinds of cases of ברירה, brera,
usually the classic cases, there's one
in, sorry, one of the main cases of ברירה, brera, classic case
is a case of separating תרומה terumah and another case is your
set in the עירוב תחומין eruv techumin to be able to go
to the שול shul that's far away from your house, but you
don't know which side the guest speaker, the scholar-in-residence was coming for
שבת. Shabbat. You don't know whether to the eastern side or the
western side, so you made an עירוב
תחומין eruv techumin on both sides.
Sorry. Yeah.
Is רב פפא's Rav Papa position of מיקמצין mikmatsin same as שמואל?
Shmuel? In other words...
sorry, yes, like שמואל. Shmuel. I'm sorry, yeah.
בטלו batlo and then you redo it again. You carve it out
from all the thing and you and then you reass...
No, that's רב. Rav.
It's בטלו, batlo, right?
It's the...
is that... yeah. בטלה מחלוקת Batla machloket is רב. Rav. שמואל Shmuel
says ללקוחות. le-lakochot. שמואל Shmuel says ויתר. viter.
Yesterday he said מיקמצין, mikmatsin, שמואל. Shmuel.
Okay, so maybe he's saying like שמואל Shmuel in this, I don't...
so it's unclear whether he's talking about this case or the previous
case, both.
I think he was talking about the previous case.
But he says בכל הני שמעתתא, bechol hani shmaisa, so it seems
it's unclear what רב פפא Rav Papa is saying exactly.
Okay, you're right. So it's a little bit tricky.
Okay, תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan.
It sort of depends how you read the סוגיא. sugya.
Sorry, if someone could get me a glass of water, it would
be very
helpful. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. שלושה שירדו לשום. shlosha sheyardu lashum.
There were three judges who went to assess the value of a
property. So רשב"ם Rashbam fills in a little bit of... thank you
so much.
So רשב"ם Rashbam fills in a little bit... What we're talking about
here is there was an inheritance, but there are also, not only
are there brothers who are dividing up the inheritance, there's also the
widow who gets a claim on מזונות mezonot and there are also
there are daughters who have a claim on their מזונות mezonot as
well.
Okay.
Thank you so much.
ירושה Yerusha is not the בית דין. Beit Din. This
is...
No, שלושה Shlosha is the בית דין. Beit Din.
Okay. שלושה Shlosha are the three דיינים dayanim who go in to
assess the value of the property.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now we have to just keep track
of rabbinic coinage here a little bit. It's going to be a
little bit tricky because we're going to be working simultaneously in two
different systems. Okay. Or different
denominations of coinage. Okay. אחד אומר במנה, Echad omer bemane, one says
that the property costs 100. שנים אומרים במאתים Shnayim omrim bematayim and
two of the judges say it costs 200. אחד אומר במאתים ושנים
אומרים במנה Echad omer bematayim ushnayim omrim bemane or one says 200
and two say 100. בטל יחיד במיעוטו. Batel yachid bemiuto. That's an
easy case. That's בטל ברוב. batel berov. That is any case where
you have two against one on a בית דין Beit Din in
a monetary case, two beats one. Okay. Either more valuable or less
valuable. Either way. That is, we assume that
the one who got it wrong, got it wrong. We don't try
to average them out in any kind of way. It's interesting though
because what we are saying is that here we're talking about evaluation
of the value of property, it might make sense just to average
the value of all of the דיינים. dayanim. But we say no,
we say if there's two against one and two of them agree,
it must be that those got it right and one of them
got it wrong. Yes.
Why is the verb ירדו? yardu?
They go to sit down in the court. Gotcha.
Or they go down into the field. They go down into the
property.
They go to field trip, right. It's interesting that okay yeah ירדו.
yardu. Some of those I mean you have certain verbs for different
kinds of processes. Right.
So a judicial process.
Right. So yeah יורדין yordin is to go down. It sounds to
me it sounds like more like they're going down into the field,
down to the field, right.
Okay.
בטל יחיד במיעוטו. Batel yachid bemiuto. אחד אומר במנה, Echad omer bemane,
one says it's 100. ואחד אומר בעשרים, Veechad omer beesrim, עשרים esrim
means
80. Why? Because עשרים esrim is 20 סלע. sela. So we have
number one says it's 100 which is 25. Number two says it's
20 which is 80. Okay.
And number three says ואחד אומר בשלושים. veechad omer bishloshim. So he
says 30 which is 120. Okay. Those are our three judges. One,
two and three.
And then we average that out, right?
No. So we're going to see. We have three different approaches to
this question. So according to תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, נידון במנה. nidon
bemane. We should take the middle value or perhaps the average value.
Depends on whether it's the average or the middle though because רשב"ם
Rashbam brings up later
in a case where the middle value is not in the middle,
that is the middle value is not equal to the average, then
you get some question.
So we have like a mean, median, and mode kind of thing.
Yeah we have different kinds of averages. It becomes, you know, adding
in modern statistics to this makes it more complicated. It's fun.
Yes it does. רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר, נידון בתשעים. Rabbi Elazar
berabbi Tzadok omer nidon betishim. He says 90. 90 halfway between
these. The average of the two lower ones. Okay.
Why?
We're
going to
see. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, עושים שומא ביניהם ומשלשין.
osim shuma
beineihem umeshalshin.
We take,
we
assess between them and we divide it into thirds. We're going to
see how that's explained. Okay. מאן דאמר נידון במנה, Man deamar nidon
bemane, מילתא מציעתא. milta metziata. So the one who says you take
100 is because you just take the middle one. Does that mean
the middle one or the average? Depends on how you read the
סוגיא sugya or different ראשונים Rishonim read differently. In this case they
happen to coincide which is why the רשב"ם Rashbam raises the question.
רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok omer, נידון בתשעים.
nidon betishim. So he says 90. קסבר האי ארעא תשעים שויא. kasavar
hai ara tishim shavei. He thinks well really
the land is probably worth 90. Okay. והאי דקאמר עשרים דקטעי עשרה
לאחוריו. vehai dekaamar esrim dekatei asara leachorav. The one who said 20
really underestimated the value by 10. He made a mistake. He said
10 less than it was worth. והאי דקאמר מנה קטעי עשרה לקמיה.
vehai dekaamar mane katea asara lekammei.
And the one who said 100 said overestimated the value by 10.
So really the real value is 90 plus or minus 10. Okay.
So that's רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק. Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok.
Wait what about the guy who said 120?
Oh so he's way off. That is the way רבי אלעזר ברבי
צדוק Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok reads this debate, these two really agree
about the correct value. They agree that the correct value is
90. And then they each fudge the numbers a little bit.
Number one and two agree? Exactly.
We're going to come back to that. Yes, the גמרא Gemara raises
that
question. Okay. והא דקאמר V'ha deka'amar מנה maneh קתני katanei יתרה yetera
לקמיה, lekamei, אדרבא adraba האי hai מאה ועשרה me'ah ve'asara שויא shaveya
והא דקאמר v'ha deka'amar מנה maneh קתני katanei יתרה yetera לאחוריו le'achorav
והא דקאמר v'ha deka'amar שמונים shmonim קתני katanei יתרה yetera לקמיה. lekamei.
So why not, why shouldn't he say, oh, number one and number
three got it right and really it should be 110 plus or
minus 10?
And number two was way off.
One equals 30, 20 equals 30? No, 120, right? Wasn't there a
120? Yes, 120. I'm going to align this for you guys.
Okay.
Because this is
זוז zuz and this is סלעים. selaim. Okay?
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, ניקוט nikot מיהת mihat תרי trei
קמאי kamai בידך beyadcha דמתורת demitorat מנה maneh לא lo מסלקי. masalkei.
So the reason why he thinks it should go like 90 is
because you should take the first two because really they really agree
that it's near a hundred.
Didn't we just say that a second ago? I understand it's saying
differently, it's just, it's
not really saying anything differently. More or less it's saying you should
take the lower two rather than the upper two. Because? Because, yeah.
No real
reason. Part of it has to do with again, think about it.
What's going on? We have an inheritance here that there are the
אחים achim who want to get the property and there's the אלמנה,
almanah, right? So if the property is worth more, right, if we
extend the property more, she gets a fixed amount and then they'll
get more property. If it's smaller, then she'll get a fixed amount
and they'll get smaller. And so the benefit, there's no way to
benefit the אלמנה almanah because she gets a fixed claim on the
entire estate. But if the property is assessed at a higher value,
it benefits the אחים. achim.
Why? She gets a bigger piece of the estate.
No, because she doesn't get a percentage amount. The כתובה ketubah guarantees
her a fixed amount.
Yes, right, right, right. To be a hundred סלע. sela.
Right. So, okay. So that's the first part. Okay, now we have
to deal with the position of אחרים. Acherim. Okay. I lost the
place. אחרים, Acherim, the third to last narrow line on עמוד ב׳.
Amud Bet. אחרים אומרים Acherim omrim עושים osim שומא shuma ביניהם beineihem
ומשלשים. umishalshim. So you assess between them and you divide into thirds.
Unclear what that means. קסברי Kasavrei האי hai ארעא ara תשעים ותלתא
ותילתא tishim utleta vetilta שויא. shaveya. So now we're going to get
a picture into this. So this was רבי אלעזר בן צדוק. Rabbi
Elazar ben Tzadok. Now we say, oh, maybe the property really is
worth 93 and a third. The real value is 93 and a
third.
Okay. And what? והא דקאמר V'ha deka'amar שמונים shmonim קתני katanei תליסר
ותילתא tlisar vetilta לאחוריה. le'achoreih. Why 93 and a third? Because it's,
we take the full range from 80 to 120, right? It's well,
it's we divide into thirds. So it's you average between 80 and
120, so it's 40 divided into three is 13 and a third,
so 93 and a third is the real
value.
Wait, aren't you just adding them all together and dividing them by
three?
No, because that would just get you to 100, which is the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So the אחרים's Acherim position is that you
take the extremes
and you divide the difference between the minimum and the maximum by
three because there are three judges.
That's 13 and a third.
13 and a third. So the real value is understood to be
93 and a third. Number two underestimated the value by 13 and
a third. Okay.
Wait, how do you get to 93 and a third from 13
and a third? It's the lower number. Correct.
So it's 80 plus, right.
Why are you adding to 80?
Because the range we have is from 80 to 120. So we're
one third of the way, the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that
question. We're going to get there. Right now the assumption is that
this is the real value, this is an underestimation, this is an
overestimation, and this is an overestimation, 100. Okay? And the real value
is here. Okay? Yeah. That's where we are right now, understanding the
אחרים.
Acherim. It depends on how many judges are...
So again, we don't actually know the real value. This is, how
can we guess what the real value is based on the disagreement
of the assessors? Right. We hope that the assessors actually know the
real value, but then they would always come out with the same
answer because it would be the real value.
Right. But then if you had four assessors you'd have a smaller
value.
No, we have only three or something. The rule is שומת הדיינים
shumat hadayanim. בשלושה, bishlosha, right?
It seems strange that...
The גמרא Gemara thinks it's strange too. They're going to get to
that at the end. They're going to say that it's a strange
position. Okay. Okay, so we're right at the end of the last
skinny line here, so וצלי תשבי דקאמר עשרים, utzli tishvi dakamar esrim,
the one who says it was worth eighty זוז. zuz. קטעי, katai,
he made a mistake, תליסר וצלי תליתא לאחוריה. tleisar utzli tleisa leacharei.
He underestimated by thirteen and a third. That's how you got from
ninety-three and a third to eighty. Okay. והאי דקאמר מנה, vehai dakamar
maneh, the one who said one hundred, okay, קטעי תליסר וצלי תליתא
לקמיה. katai tleisar utzli tleisa lekamei. He really thought that it was
was one
hundred and six and two-thirds. Okay. He overestimated by thirteen and a
third. ודין הוא vadin hu דלימא טפי, dilima tfei, really he should
have said more, he should have said one hundred six and two-thirds.
והאי דלא
קאמר, vehai delo kaamar, the fact that he did not say one
hundred six and two-thirds, סבר savar מסתייא דקא מטפינא כולי האי חבראי.
mistaya deka matfina kulei hai chavrai. It's enough that I'm saying already
twenty more than my friend.
Wait, how'd he get one hundred and six and two-thirds?
Because that's thirteen and a third above ninety-three and a third. So
now so the position, right, רבי אלעזר בר צדוק, Rabbi Elazar bar
Tzadok, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says one hundred, right? תנא קמא's
Tanna Kamma very simple. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says one hundred. רבי
אלעזר בר צדוק Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok
says that it's he says ninety plus or minus ten. And אחרים
Acherim say it's ninety-three and a third plus or minus thirteen and
a third. Okay,
which gets you eighty and gets you one hundred and six and
two-thirds. One hundred and six and two-thirds rounds down to one hundred.
We're still assuming that number three is way off.
So both of these positions agree that the third דיין dayan is
totally wrong and it's a question of how do we assess the
errors that the two דיינים dayanim made. Is there
any
logic to why, like I don't understand why we're assuming he's way
off, why are we including him in our calculations?
Because רבי אלעזר בר צדוק Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok only cares about
one and two, right? It's basic it's based on an average of
one and two. Okay. והאחרים ve-ha'acherim position is based on an average
of one and three, right?
And then we divide into thirds. I understand,
but if we're
saying that
three is way off, why are we averaging between one and three?
Right. That's a good question. The גמרא Gemara doesn't like this position
but they have to explain it to you as best as they
can. Okay.
And the thing about the אחרים Acherim is that their starting number
is already a derivative estimation.
Well again, all of this is derivative on the data that we
have based on שומת shumat הדיינים. hadayanim We don't actually know anything.
All we know is these three people looked at this field, one
said one hundred, one said eighty, and one said one hundred and
twenty. That's all we know. How do we take these three pieces
of data,
right, but the אחרים Acherim starting position of ninety-three and a third
is already a derivative of an estimation from the other. In other
words, you know what I'm saying?
Yeah, but so is this ninety.
This ninety is an average of one hundred and eighty.
No, but the ninety is starting with the basic assessment.
So is this. No. This is eighty plus one hundred and twenty
divided by three. No it's not.
It's it's
one hundred and twenty minus eighty divided by three.
Minus eighty. Right. There's another step.
So yeah, it's the same.
No. You see this?
This is one hundred minus eighty. It's it's eighty plus one hundred
minus eighty over two. And this is eighty plus one hundred and
twenty minus eighty over three. This is plus also. Right?
It's the same steps. It's just using different data. Okay. דחתא. dakhta.
Okay. So the and the
so the point is that because why didn't he say one hundred
and six and two-thirds? Because he really said, oh, it's I'm already
saying twenty more than my friend so I should round down to
one hundred. Okay. אדרבה. adrava. So the גמרא Gemara is frustrated. The
גמרא Gemara asks אדרבה adrava on the third wide line. אדרבה האי
ארעא מאה ותליסר וצלי תליתא שויא. adrava hai ara mea utleisar utzli
tleisa shavya. You should say that it's the land is worth one
hundred and thirteen and a third. Okay, alternatively, one hundred and thirteen
and a third is one hundred is thirteen and a third above
one hundred. That is we should say not eighty plus one hundred
and twenty minus eighty over three, we could say one hundred plus
one hundred and twenty minus eighty over three. Okay. But then what
would be, where would we be? Okay, האי ארעא מאה ותליסר וצלי
תליתא שויא. hai ara mea utleisar utzli tleisa shavya. והאי דקאמר מנה,
vehai dakamar maneh, the one who said one hundred, קטעי תליסר וצלי
תליתא לאחוריה. katai tleisar utzli tleisa leacharei. He undervalued it by thirteen
and a third. והאי דקאמר שלשים, vehai dakamar sloshim, and the one
who says one hundred and twenty, קטעי תליסר וצלי תליתא לקמיה. katai
tleisar utzli tleisa lekamei. And he overestimated the value of a thirteen
and a third, but then what? Then
he should really be one hundred and twenty. twenty six and two-thirds.
So why does he only say one twenty? Okay. ובדין הוא דקאמר
טפי, Uvedin hu de-ka'amar tefei, he should have said more, סבר מסתפינא
מטפינא כולי האי חבראי. savar mistafi'na matpina kulei hai chavrai. It's enough
that I'm already saying twenty more than my friend number one. So
meaning, this is the real value, right? This is number three. This
is the real value
and this is number
one.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't like this because why would you assume
that one and two are more correct than one and three? And
therefore this process doesn't make any sense. Okay. נקוט מיהא תרי קמאי
בידך,
nakot mi-ha
terei kama'ei be-yadcha, you should take the first two in your hand,
that means the lowest two, דמתורת מאה לא מפקת ליה, de-mitorat me'ah
lo mafkat lei, because really the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is really
correct. That is the starting assumption of רבי אלעזר בר רבי צדוק
Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok and אחרים Acherim is that you never really
get away from one hundred. That is the average is one hundred.
So the answer privileges the position which coincides with the average as
well. That is, we should take the lower one which uses the
one hundred, or which gets us an answer sort of closer to
one hundred, the lower end rather than the higher end. Okay. אמר
רב הונא הלכה כאחרים. Amar Rav Huna halacha ke-Acherim. So the הלכה
halacha follows the אחרים, Acherim, that is this one, the real value
is ninety three and one third, okay, according to רב הונא. Rav
Huna. אמר רב אשי טעמא דאחרים לא ידעינן הלכתא עבדינן כוותייהו? Amar
Rav Ashi ta'ama de-Acherim lo yadina hilcheta avdina ke-vateihu? So רב אשי
Rav Ashi says back what are you talking about? אחרים Acherim make
no sense. Like everyone was saying, the אחרים's Acherim position is very
strange. So if the אחרים's Acherim position makes no sense, then we
shouldn't פסקן הלכה pasken halacha like them. That's very interesting though. The
question still remains. That is, it's possible to follow a הלכתי halachic
opinion even if you don't like the rationale. You could just say,
okay, we're going to follow this algorithm, right? Take the highest and
lowest ones, average them, and then add it to the lowest one,
you know. So but רב אשי Rav Ashi doesn't like that. That
is רב הונא Rav Huna was willing to say, okay, follow the
position that you don't like because just we should follow אחרים. Acherim.
Maybe because it's הלכה כרבים, halacha ke-rabbim, maybe any number of other
reasons. Okay. So now we have a challenge, a sort of a
similar case from a ברייתא. Beraita. תנו דייני גולה, Tanu dayyanei golah,
no, it's not really a ברייתא, Beraita, it's actually a מימרא meimra
because דייני גולה dayyanei golah is שמואל Shmuel and קרנא Karna who
are two very early אמוראים. Amoraim. So דייני גולה, dayyanei golah, the
judges of the diaspora, who are שמואל Shmuel and קרנא, Karna, תנו
דייני גולה עושין שום ביניהם ומשלשין. tanu dayyanei golah osin shum beineihem
u-meshaleshin. So according to דייני גולה, dayyanei golah, we should follow the
position of אחרים, Acherim, that is take the maximum and minimum, average
them, and then add it to the minimum case, okay, ומשלשין. u-meshaleshin.
So אמר רב הונא הלכתא כדייני גולה. Amar Rav Huna hilcheta ke-dayyanei
golah. And רב הונא Rav Huna had said the הלכה halacha was
like דייני גולה dayyanei golah in a similar case. אמר רב אשי
טעמא דדייני גולה לא ידעינן הלכתא עבדינן כוותייהו? Amar Rav Ashi ta'ama
de-dayyanei golah lo yadina hilcheta avdina ke-vateihu? And רב אשי Rav Ashi
again asked the same question. If you don't understand their principle, why
you know this is such a convoluted calculation, then why should we
follow הלכה halacha like them? So מחלוקת machloket between רב הונא Rav
Huna and רב אשי Rav Ashi about whether or not to follow
this assessment process or not.
דייני גולה dayyanei golah agree with אחרים. Acherim.
Okay. So דייני גולה, dayyanei golah, so it's interesting actually. You have
a lot more authority
of רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna always פוסקן posken
like the אחרים Acherim position in both versions, and רב אשי Rav
Ashi always asks him the same question, that is, a question which
is, if you don't like their reasoning, then why should you follow
them? So מחלוקת machloket between רב הונא Rav Huna and רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, how to פסקן pasken in this case in the conclusion.
It seems as a statistician, I find this entire סוגיא sugya to
be bizarre.
Well, the conclusion הלכה למעשה halacha le-ma'aseh seems like we follow תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. So because רב אשי Rav Ashi is frustrated, so
רב הונא Rav Huna was over here, right? And
and רב אשי Rav Ashi is over here.
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, if רב אשי Rav Ashi is frustrated, I
can well,
you can join רב אשי. Rav Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi is
a good person to have on your team.
Dan, I have a question. How come the number how come the
number 90 is mentioned and not 80?
Because 90 was 100 was the average of 100 and 80.
Right, that's where 90, that is when you ignore this one, average
these two and you say oh, the real value must be 90
and the one who underestimated underestimated by 10 and the one who
overestimated overestimated by 10.
So when it says at the very beginning of the סוגיא, sugya,
רבי אלעזר בר רבי צדוק אומר נידון בתשעים, Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok
omer nidon be-tishim, yes, that's what he's doing.
That's רבי אלעזר בר רבי צדוק's Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok position, which
we don't follow.
Right, he's saying, oh, the
two lowest values are each in error of equal amount. Right? Fundamentally,
what does רבי אלעזר בר רבי צדוק Rabbi Elazar berabbi Tzadok say?
You take the lowest two and average them because they each erred
equally. This position actually says all three positions are in error, no
one got it right, but you take into... to account of the
two extremes and the lowest one underestimated by a certain amount and
therefore the middle one overestimated an equal amount but rounded down out
of consideration for his colleagues and this one is totally off is
is three steps right? Because if the real value is 93 and
a third then this is right? It's 93 and a third plus
minus 93 and a third and also the third position is plus
26 and two thirds which is a third one right? So those
are the three different errors.
And translate that into the algebraic formula that you wrote?
Well that's just because that's two of these right? 40 divided by
three is 13 and a third so 26 and two thirds is
two increments that's the third 120 is two increments above the average
position right? Like either you erred this way you erred this way
and rounded down or you erred all the way over here. Those
are the three different...
Oh I see what you're saying. In other words the 120 minus
80 divided by three you get 13 and
a third and then
you add it to the 80.
Right so this is the אחרים. Acherim.
I don't they know the גמרא Gemara says רב אשי Rav Ashi
says it doesn't make any sense. I'm not sure it doesn't make
any sense it's just a little bit strange. Yes Charlie.
Yeah תוספות Tosafos has a note that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
is actually calling for the median to be used.
Right that that רשב"ם Rashbam discusses that whether it's meant to be
the average or the median.
And I know the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens that.
The רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens it's the median I know the רשב"ם
Rashbam I forget now where the רשב"ם Rashbam is. I think it's
on עמוד א. Amud Alef. רשב"ם Rashbam at least discusses that
and רשב"ם Rashbam says...
Yeah the last רשב"ם Rashbam on עמוד א Amud Alef מילתא מציעתא
דבר שווה הכריע בין שניהם הוסיף חמישה על הממעיט ופוחת חמישה מן
המרבה ובדין הוא דתידון כוותיה דמנה דהא תרוויהו של שלשים ושל מנה
מודו דשווה מנה ונראה בעיני דהוא הדין אם אמר בכ"ח סלעים דלא
הוי מציעתא
כל כך.
Milta metziata davar shaveh hichria bein sheneihem hosif chamisha al hamam’it upochet
chamisha min
hamarbeh uvidin hu detidun kvatei demaneh deha tarvaihu shel sheloshim veshel maneh
modu deshaveh maneh venir’eh be’einai dehu hadin im amar bekof-chet sela’im dela
havei metziata kol kach. So he says sounds like רשב"ם Rashbam is
saying you use the mode. You average them even if the claim
was not 30 but was 28
because really it's an agreement that that 25 is right and then
you go from there. So it's really
two against one outvoting him like the previous part of this סוגיא
sugya which actually fits the סוגיא sugya very well but then doesn't
make any sense for a lot of other cases. Okay next משנה
Mishnah we'll do a little the first סוגיא sugya of the next
משנה. Mishnah. האומר לחבירו Haomer lachaveiro חצי שדה אני מוכר לך. chatzi
sadeh ani mocher lach.
I'm going to sell you half a field. משמנין ביניהם ונוטל חצי
שדהו. mishmenim beineihem venotel chatzi sadehu.
You assess between them and he takes half of his field. Okay
seems pretty straightforward. חציה בדרום אני מוכר לך
chatziya bedarom ani
mocher
lach
if I'm selling you the half in the south so משמנין ביניהם
ונוטל חציה בדרום. mishmenim beineihem venotel chatziya bedarom. Okay
so he they do an assessment between them and he takes the
half that's in the south so it was more explicit. Okay. והוא
מקבל עליו מקום הגדר חריץ ובן חריץ vehu mekabel alav mekom hageder
charitz uven charitz and the purchaser assumes the responsibility for guaranteeing the
fence and the ditch and the בן חריץ ben charitz excuse me
which is half a ditch. וכמה הוא חריץ ששה טפחים vekhama hu
charitz shishah tefachim
so the ditch is six טפחים tefachim wide. ובן חריץ שלשה uven
charitz sheloshah and the secondary ditch the you know is only three
טפחים tefachim wide. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן. amar Rebbi Chiyya bar Abba amar
Rebbi Yochanan. So רבי חייא
בר אבא Rebbi Chiyya bar Abba said quoting רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
לוקח נוטל כחוש שבו. loke’ach notel kachush shebo. The purchaser always gets
the short end of the stick because the purchaser is in a
disadvantaged position we say generally יד על התחתונה yad al hatachtonah so
this that's why so he's saying in this assessment in the שומא
shuma in the value of the field the purchaser will get the
cheaper half of the field.
What's the can you translate כחוש שבו? kachush shebo?
כחוש kachush כחוש kachush like skinny shrunken one right?
Like a steak that's not a fatty steak in כשרות kashrus we
say right the contrasting שמן shamen and כחוש kachush right? Okay. So
אמר ליה רבי חייא בר אבא לרבי יוחנן. amar lei Rebbi Chiyya
bar Abba leRebbi Yochanan. So רבי חייא בר אבא Rebbi Chiyya bar
Abba says back to רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan okay והאנן משמנין ביניהם
תנן. veha’anan mishmenim beineihem tenan. The משנה Mishnah says we assess the
value. So what are you talking about that he takes the cheaper
half? What does that even
mean? אמר ליה amar lei אדאכלת כפניתא בבבל. adachalta kafneita beVavel.
You've been fattening yourself up on dates in בבל. Bavel. You haven't
been learning your משניות Mishnayos properly. תרגמנא מסיפא. Targamna mi-seifa. No, you
have to explain the רישא reisha of the משנה Mishnah from the
סיפא seifa of the משנה. Mishnah. דקתני, Dekatani, סיפא, seifa, חציה בדרום
אני מוכר לך. chatziyah ba-darom ani mocher lach.
The Rashi shows two pictures of date palms.
Oh, see there you go. So you know you've been spending too
much time in the הפקר פיו Hefker Pio in yeshiva eating snacks
and not enough time learning your
משניות, Mishnayos, says רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
could be very sharp. Okay. חציה בדרום אני מוכר לך. Chatziyah ba-darom
ani mocher lach. He said in the סיפא, seifa, I'm selling you
the southern half. So he was explicit about which half he was
selling. משמנינן בינייהו. Mishamninan beinei'hu. But the משנה Mishnah still says you
have to take an assessment of the property. Why? ונוטל חציה בדרום.
Ve-notel chatziyah ba-darom. You take the half in the south. ואמאי משמנינן?
Ve-amai mishamninan? Why do you have to do an
assessment? ואמאי משמנינן בינייהו? Ve-amai mishamninan beinei'hu? והא חציה בדרום אמר ליה?
Ve-ha chatziyah ba-darom amar lei? He said explicitly he was selling the
southern half. אלא לדמי. Ela le-damei. It must be that the assessment
is divided half is half the field by value, not by area.
והכא נמי לדמי. Ve-hacha nami le-damei. Therefore so too in this case
you split the field in terms of its value, which might be
sixty forty in terms of the land area. And then the purchaser
gets the smaller field based on land area. Smaller field, which would
be worth half according to that. Let's just do the last סוגיא
sugya just so we can finish the
פרק. perek. Okay. מקבל עליו מקום גדר. Me-kabel alav mekom geder. Okay.
So תנא, Tana, חריץ מבחוץ ובן חריץ מבפנים. Charitz mi-bachutz u-ven charitz
mi-bifnim. So the חריץ, charitz, the ditch, it was taught in this
in this
תוספתא Tosefta I think or ברייתא Braisa that the ditch goes on
the outside of the field and the בן חריץ, ben charitz, the
secondary ditch—I don't know they have a better translation of בן חריץ
ben charitz in the Steinsaltz or the
Artscroll—smaller ditch. Yeah. בן חריץ. Ben charitz. So the חריץ charitz is
on the outside, בן חריץ ben charitz is on the inside.
Yeah, they have a picture here
of how the irrigation ditches have been are set up properly. Okay.
וזה וזה אחורי גדר. Ve-zeh ve-zeh achorei geder. And both of them
go behind, that is, inside the wall. So that is what's the
case? If we're talking about where he bought the field, so we
had the whole field and he sold half the field. And then
he said you, the purchaser, right, the לוקח, loke'ach, you have the
responsibility to build a גדר. geder. So the גדר geder has to
be here. Okay.
And then the חריץ charitz is מבחוץ mi-bachutz outside of the field.
So that's here is the חריץ. charitz. And then there's another ditch
here which is the בן חריץ. ben charitz. So he gets an
even smaller field because he has a responsibility to include this whole
piece of the גדר geder and חריץ charitz and בן חריץ ben
charitz within his property that he just purchased.
And he has to build it.
And he has to build it. Yeah, presumably. Well to build the
fence, we go back to the first פרק perek now, maybe they
have to split the value of the fence, I'm not sure now.
Okay. וזה וזה אחורי גדר. Ve-zeh ve-zeh achorei geder. So both of
them are within the wall. כדי שלא תהא חיה קופצת. Kedei shelo
tehei chayah kofetzet. So that there's no way that an animal could
jump in ולאביד חריץ—so u-l'avid charitz okay, כדי שלא תהא חיה קופצת.
kedei shelo tehei chayah kofetzet. So that's why you dig a ditch,
so that if you have a ditch here next to your wall,
then an animal cannot jump over, or I guess from this side,
the animal can't jump over the fence because the fence is functionally
even higher than it was because if this is ground level, then
this is an irrigation ditch, but it's also to make the fence
the fence
taller. Okay. Or actually this doesn't seem right. Maybe it means that
the בן חריץ ben charitz is here and the חריץ charitz is
here.
That is, they're both אחורי גדר. achorei geder. This is the גדר
geder and there's one on either side so that either way the
חיה chayah can't jump. That makes more sense, but I'm not sure.
Okay. ולאביד חריץ. U-l'avid charitz.
Yeah. So it doesn't say מבחוץ ומבפנים. mi-bachutz u-mi-bifnim.
חריץ מבחוץ. Charitz mi-bachutz. Right. So this is the לוקח's loke'ach property.
So חריץ charitz is on the מבחוץ, mi-bachutz, is on the outer
side. So this is the property line. Right? This is the מוכר.
mocher. Here's the property line. Then here's the חריץ, charitz, the גדר,
geder, and the בן חריץ. ben charitz. And then he finally has
a field over here. So this is three טפחים, tefachim, this is
six טפחים, tefachim, and then this is however wide a גדר geder
is. Okay? So I think that makes sense because this way the
חריץ charitz is on the outside, the בן חריץ ben charitz is
on the inside, the גדר geder is here, and animals can't jump
either way because there is a ditch that contributes to deepening the
height
of the wall so the animals will have a harder time.
So that and I guess in the where would the irrigation ditch
be other than אחורי גדר? achorei geder? No, אחורי גדר achorei geder
meaning next to on either side of the meaning you could just
dig a ditch down the middle of your field or something like
that. So this ditch is not only for irrigation, it's also as
the גמרא Gemara says to prevent the animals from jumping over the
fence. Okay. ולאביד חריץ ולאביד בן חריץ. U-l'avid charitz ve-lo l'avid ben
charitz. So maybe he should be allowed to. dig a חריץ charitz
on his side but not to dig the בן חריץ, ben charitz,
and then he can have an extra three טפחים tefachim of field
and just take the liability? Like this way the animals won't get
into his field because he has a deep ditch on this side.
But here's the problem. You didn't dig a ditch on the other
side. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says לאבי חריץ השתא נמי לא קפצה
חריץ מרחיקה מן הגדר. la'avi charitz hashta nami lo kaftza charitz marchika
min hageder. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so איידי דרווח קיימא
בגוויה, aidi deravach kayama be'gavei, so now that there's this width of
six טפחים, tefachim, you've entered into, you've gotten into the point where
it's now behind the wall, so it's possible to jump over, וקפצה.
ve'kaftza. ולאעביד בן חריץ ולא ליעביד חריץ, u'le'avid ben charitz velo la'avid
charitz, and if he makes only the בן חריץ ben charitz
and not the חריץ, charitz, so איידי דקטין קיימא אשפתיה וקפצה. aidi
diktin kayama asfatei ve'kaftza. So then because it's smaller, you could stand,
you know, if it's only three טפחים tefachim and then the fence,
the animal could stand here and jump over to there. So there's
all this concern about the animals jumping the
fence. Okay. וכמה בין חריץ לחריץ טפח. ve'kama bein charitz le'charitz tefach.
So what's the difference between a חריץ charitz and a בן חריץ
ben charitz is only one טפח. tefach. That, so that seems to,
did I say depth or width? It seems to
contradict what the משנה Mishna had said.
The משנה Mishna had said a
חריץ charitz is six and בן חריץ ben charitz is three. The
רשב"ם Rashbam is not helpful here. I don't have a good answer
for that. We could say הדרן עלך בית כור. hadran alach beit
kor. Between
the ditches is the width of the, וכמה בין חריץ לבין חריץ
טפח? ve'kama bein charitz levein charitz tefach?
But that's the width of the גדר? geder? That doesn't seem very
wide for a fence. That does not make sense. Yeah, I'm not
sure. I mean that's a very, I will look into this and
I will have a good explanation tomorrow morning. We'll start with that.
It would have to be like a wooden fence you assume. But
they don't have a wooden fence, they wouldn't waste wood on that.